<metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Metropolitan Council</origin><pubdate>20211227</pubdate><title>Functional Class Roads - Existing</title><mgmg1cid>N/A</mgmg1cid><pubinfo><publish>Metropolitan Council</publish></pubinfo><onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metc-trans-fnctnl-cls-rds</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>The functional class roads layer contains major roads and highways in the Twin Cities seven county metropolitan area.  

In 2021, MnDOT did a full review of the metro area functional class system at the direction of the Federal Highway Administration. The result of this review was a large scale change of the metro functional class, including addition of many collectors. This file is markedly different than the version dated 2020. Questions about this process should be directed to metadata contact. 

As of Sept 2019, the line work for this dataset is from the Metro Regional Centerline Collaborative (MRCC). The previous versions were based on the NCompass data. Data has been reviewed for errors and dropped links, but no guarantee is made in accuracy for minor linework errors. Please report any issues found in linework to Rachel Wiken (contact on Metadata). 

The specific classifications assigned to the roadways resulted from efforts of the Land Transportation Committee, Transportation Technical Advisory Committee and the Transportation Advisory Board as specified in the transportation planning process, using federal rules and guidelines. The final product was approved with Metropolitan Council concurrence. 

The 'A' minor arterial network was adopted by the Transportation Advisory Board in 1993.

Attributes include functional classification code and road name.

Please note that changes to the status of the planned functional class roads MAY impact the classification of this layer.  Please confer with Metropolitan Council staff if you have questions.</abstract><purpose>To assist the Twin Cities Metropolitan Planning Organization with transportation planning and project programming in the Twin Cities region.</purpose><supplinf>Twin Cities seven county metropolitan area.  This includes the counties of Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington in Minnesota.</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20211227</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><current>Includes linework from the MRCC</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>As needed</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-94.012</westbc><eastbc>-92.732</eastbc><northbc>45.415</northbc><southbc>44.471</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekt>None</themekt><themekey>roads, streets, highways, functional class, centerlines, major roads, transportation, regional solicitation, Functional Class Roads, MRCC</themekey></theme><place><placekey>Twin Cities, Anoka County, Carver County, Dakota County, Hennepin County, Ramsey County, Scott County, Washington County</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>None. This dataset is public domain under the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13). If the dataset is not available from the Online Linkage in Section 6, please contact the Distribution Contact Person.</accconst><useconst>None. This dataset is public domain under the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).</useconst><browse><browsen>https://resources.gisdata.mn.gov/pub/gdrs/data/pub/us_mn_state_metc/trans_fnctnl_cls_rds/metadata/preview.jpg</browsen></browse><native>ArcGIS 9x</native><crossref><citeinfo><title>Functional Class Roads - Planned, Major Highways. Metro Regional Centerline Collaborative Roads </title></citeinfo></crossref><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Dave Burns</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Planning Analyst</cntpos><cntaddr><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1887</cntvoice><cntemail>david.burns@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>Functional classification values were entered and checked by Metropolitan Council GIS staff and double checked by Metropolitan Council Transportation Planning staff.

Please note that changes to the status of the planned functional class roads MAY impact the classification of this layer.  Please confer with Metropolitan Council staff if you have questions.</attraccr></attracc><logic>The dataset is topologically 'clean'.</logic><complete>Entire seven county geographic area is covered.</complete><lineage><srcinfo><srcscale /></srcinfo><procstep><procdesc>To create this dataset, a new Metropolitan Council functional class attribute was added to the road centerline file. Roads without functional class values were removed.UNIQUE_ID can be used to connect this file to the full Roads Centerline. 

The specific classifications assigned to the roadways resulted from efforts of the Land Transportation Committee, Transportation Technical Advisory Committee and the Transportation Advisory Board as specified in the transportation planning process, using federal rules and guidelines.  The final product was approved with Metropolitan Council concurrence.</procdesc></procstep></lineage></dataqual><spdoinfo><indspref>None</indspref><direct>Vector</direct><mgmg3obj>arcs, nodes</mgmg3obj><mgmg3til>One layer for entire seven county region.</mgmg3til></spdoinfo><eainfo><overview><eaover>LINE ATTRIBUTES:
(In addition to the default ArcInfo attributes)



Feature Unique ID (UNIQUE_ID) : MRCC ID 

Street Name Full (ST_CONCAT): Full street name.
 


Alternate Street Name 1 (ST_NAME_A1):  Alternate street name 1.
 


Alternate Street Name 2 (ST_NAME_A2):  Alternate street name 2.


ONEWAY: Y yes or N no 

 
FUN_CLAS:  (Numerical) Functional classification assigned to the road

             100 = Principal Arterial 
             211 = A-minor Augmentor
             212 = A-Minor Reliever
             213 = A-Minor Expander
             214 = A-Minor Connector
             220 = Other Arterial
             310 = Major Collector
             320 = Minor Collector
             



FC_NAME:   (Text) Functional classification assigned to the road</eaover><eadetcit>None</eadetcit></overview></eainfo><distinfo><resdesc>FunctionalClassRoads</resdesc><distliab>NOTICE:  The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).  THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes.  The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate.  You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data.  You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features.  If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>Shape file</formname><formvern>ArcGIS 9x</formvern><transize>2.2 Meg. for zip file.</transize></digtinfo></digform><ordering>See Online Linkage Below</ordering></stdorder><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS System Administrator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1561</cntvoice><cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20211227</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Dave Burns</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>Planning Analyst</cntpos><cntaddr><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1887</cntvoice><cntemail>david.burns@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><Esri><ModDate>20110721</ModDate><ModTime>13152800</ModTime></Esri><mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20110721</mdDateSt><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref></metadata>